Rhiannon: How can we tell
if someone is being bullied?
Leah: If a child’s belongings are
forever getting 'lost' or damaged
or they never seem to have any
money, this may indicate bullying.
If they are suffering from physical
injuries or unexplained bruises, maybe
they don’t want to go to school or feign
illness, or they are not doing well in
class, this may also be an indication.
If they generally become nervous, lose
confidence and become withdrawn, or have
problems with eating and sleeping this
can be an indication that the child or
young person could be being bullied.
Rhiannon: Any child can
be bullied for any reason.
If a child is seen as different in
some way or seen as an easy target,
they can be even more at risk.
This might be because of their
race or ethnic background, gender,
sexual orientation or could be just
because they have low self-esteem,
seem shy or introverted or appear
anxious and lack assertiveness.
Leah: They may be bullied for the way they
look, the colour of their hair, if they
wear glasses or if they have a disability.
Rhiannon: Some may be a target because of
their interests or hobbies, they are new
to an area, they have changed schools,
or due to their family circumstances.
Leah: Sometimes people can even be bullied
for things we wouldn’t associate with
bullying, such as being good looking,
popular, clever or having nice things.
Rhiannon: Bullying is all about
causing hurt to others repeatedly,
with ongoing damaging effects and the
bully gains satisfaction and a sense
of power, from treating others badly.
Leah: A young person who becomes visibly
upset at name-calling may increasingly
become the focus of attention and may
be seen as a soft target, someone who is
"easy to wind up” but not every at-risk
person will be subject to bullying.
Rhiannon: Maybe there isn’t a bully
around or maybe the person is more
self-assured and self-confident and not
as susceptible to bullying in general.
In these cases bullying may not be
the course and we need to look to
other factors, but it is always worth
being mindful of the possibilities.